Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories 2010-2016
AFC 2015/048
Luft, Benjamin J.
approximately 2067 items
522 moving images; digital, mov and mp4
1327 graphic materials; digital, jpg, pdf, tif, and png
218 manuscripts; digital, pdf and pptx
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of 328 oral history interviews of individuals impacted by the September 11, 2001 World Trade Center disaster, and interviewee's photographs and manuscript materials documenting their experiences at the site. The collection primarily contains first-person narratives told by World Trade Center site disaster workers: police officers, firefighters, construction workers, demolition specialists, ironworkers, veterinarians, paramedics, and other volunteers at the site.
Provenance
The collection was created by Dr. Benjamin Luft and associates as part of their wellness program for World Trade Center first responders. The American Folklife Center has received two donations from Dr. Luft: 199 interviews in 2015 and 129 interviews in 2017.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected.
Additional Guides
The American Folklife Center retains a copy of Dr. Luft's original metadata spreadsheet. The spreadsheet contains additional data concerning interviewees, including occupation, age, hometown, and span of time worked at the WTC disaster site. Please contact the Folklife Reading Room to access the spreadsheet.
Related Material
Dr. Luft gave a lecture at the Library prior to donating his collection: We're Not Leaving": responders' oral histories redefine 9/11 lecture by Benjamin Luft 2011 November 10. (AFC 2011/056). https://lccn.loc.gov/2017655301
Dr. Luft also published a book of excerpts from the collection's interviews: We're not leaving: 9/11 responders tell their stories of courage, sacrifice, and renewal by Dr. Benjamin Luft. https://lccn.loc.gov/2012358325
Access and Restrictions
The Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
The full names of some interviewees were redacted from recordings and collection metadata prior to the collection's acquisition by the American Folklife Center. In accordance with these interviewees' wishes and agreements with Dr. Luft, the Folklife Center does not know or have documentation of these individuals' full names.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials applies.
Biographical Note
Dr. Benjamin J. Luft is the Edmund D. Pellegrino Professor of Medicine at the Stony Brook University and an internationally recognized expert in the treatment of Lyme disease and AIDS-related conditions. In 2001, Dr. Luft, a native New Yorker, responded to 9/11 as Chair of the Department of Medicine at the State University of New York at Stony Brook (Stony Brook University). He established a 9/11 clinical center, the Stony Brook WTC Wellness Program for the 9/11 responder community, initiated an oral history project with 9/11 first responders, has published the book We're not leaving: 9/11 responders tell their stories of courage, sacrifice, and renewal, produced the film 9/11: An American Requiem and developed curriculum materials from these interviews.
Scope and Content
Collection of 328 video interviews and supporting photographs, videos, and manuscripts. Also included are Dr. Luft's related published materials. The interviews, which are in Series 1, are primarily first-person narratives told by World Trade Center site disaster workers: police officers, firefighters, construction workers, demolition specialists, ironworkers, veterinarians, paramedics, and other volunteers at the site. The interviews were conducted by Dr. Luft and his associates. Some individuals' full names have been redacted - please see Access and Restrictions note for more information. The recordings vary in length, but generally run from thirty minutes to 2 hours. The supporting images, videos, and manuscripts were given to Dr. Luft by interviewees. These supporting records, which are primarily visual materials, document events immediately following the attack on the World Trade Center through the cleanup of the site. Dr. Luft's published materials in Series 2 include the feature-length documentary he produced, 9/11: An American Requiem, recordings of his seminar 9/11: The Anatomy of a Health Care Disaster, a digital copy of his book of interview excerpts, and four themed teaching aid videos.
Interviews number 188, 228, and 271 and their accompanying documentation were destroyed by Dr. Luft at the request of the interviewees. These deletions occurred prior to the American Folklife Center's acquisition of the collection.
Arrangement
The Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories is organized in two series:
Series 1. Oral History Interviews 2010-2016.
Series 2. Published Materials 2011-2013.
The interview summaries featured in this finding aid's contents list were written by Dr. Luft and his associates.
See the Scope and Content note for additional information relevant to the collection's arrangement.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Luft, Benjamin J.
Organizations
World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.: 1970-2001)
Subjects
Air--Pollution--Health aspects--New York (State)--New York.; First responders--New York (State)--New York--Interviews.; Post-traumatic stress disorder--New York (State)--New York.; Rescue work--New York (State)--New York--Anecdotes.; Search and rescue operations--New York (State)--New York--Anecdotes.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001--Personal narratives.; Terrorism--United States.
Places
New York (N.Y.); World Trade Center Site (New York, N.Y.)
Titles
Benjamin Luft collection of September 11th oral histories
Form/Genre
Digital photographs--Color--2010-2020.; Interviews.; Oral histories.; Personal narratives.; Video recordings.
Container List
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, April 9, 2010 through November 4, 2016
  Formats are grouped together by interview. Each interview, listed here as subseries, has one digital folder containing at least the master interview video recording(s). Some folders also contain related photographs, videos, or manuscripts donated by interviewees, or a transcript of the interview. The counts of each format per interview are listed in the subseries contents. The interview summaries featured here were written by Dr. Luft and his associates. Recording lengths are hours, minutes, seconds format (hh:mm:ss).
  - John Feal oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, April 9, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 001
    John, demolition foreman and presently an advocate, was in Nanuet, NY in charge of a large demolition job on September 11, 2001. When he heard of the attacks, he shut down the job and returned to the New York City immediately. In the first few days of the clean-up work, a steel beam landed on his foot. After 10 days in the hospital, he developed gangrene, and eventually, he lost half of his foot. He spent a total of 11 weeks in a hospital bed, but complete recovery took much longer. John reveals his mental struggle after this injury and how the experience altered his perception of his life and what is important to him as a person. Between 2001 and 2006, John underwent multiple surgeries and spent this extended period in a cast and on crutches. He would not be able to work at his job again, but his injury inspired him to advocate for other responders, and he founded the FealGood Foundation. In his work as an advocate, he always found those who were worse off than him and he learned the best way to deal with the many tragedies of September 11, 2001 disaster was to focus on the positive and the unity of the human spirit that he witnessed as a responder.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - Anthony Flammia and Wendy Flammia oral history interview conducted by Janet Lavelle, April 9, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 002
    In September, 2001, Anthony lived in Oakdale, NY and commuted into the city where he was an NYPD officer assigned to highway patrol. He and his wife, Wendy, were expecting their first child. That morning he was assigned to Queens Boulevard for speeding violations. As he opened his newspaper, he heard over the radio about a small plane that hit the WTC and he waited for further direction. He was directed to return to the station and partner up. Not knowing what to expect, Anthony and his partner grabbed shotguns and ammunition before heading downtown. As they approached the midtown tunnel, they could see the towers on fire and smoke filling the sky. At the site, Anthony was assigned to be an escort. He had just returned from escorting nurses to the side when the first tower fell. He and his partner ran. He recalls the tower falling sounded like a freight train magnified by 5,000 and from here his memory is a blur. Throughout the day, he remembers setting up a command post, evacuating from a gas main break, searching for radios, and more escorts. Altogether, Anthony worked a little over 200 hours between the morgue and escorts of important persons, workers, and the families of deceased police officers. He really began to feel the weight of the event when escorting the families. The excitement of his first child brought some positive but for the most part he ran on auto-pilot with little time to cope. In December of 2001, he was called in for a small village police job on Long Island and as he settled in he began to feel off but attributed the feeling to the change of environment. He noticed his health decline gradually until after an incident in February of 2007 when he was forced to retire. Now Anthony and his wife, Wendy, are working to get him better and as a family, understand what PTSD is and what it does to responders. They both agree there is still a lot of healing ahead of them. Anthony says responders are a different breed and if asked to respond again, he would do it in a heartbeat.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - Glen Klein oral history interview conducted by Melodie Guerrera, April 9, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 003
    Glen worked as a NYPD officer in the Emergency Medical Services unit on 9/11/2001. He worked in the S.W.A.T /Rescue unit for 109 Precinct in Flushing, Queens. Glen states, “We were the guys police officers called when they needed help.” Glen was at home when he got a call from a friend who told him one of the towers was hit by a plane. He initially thought his friend was playing a prank on him. He turned on the T.V. and saw the damage. He prepared to rush to work, taking a direct route on the Long Island Northern State Parkway to his precinct in Flushing, Queens. He states he was driving “about a 100 miles an hour” when he saw a police officer telling him to pull over. To save time, Glen flashed his badge at the police officer and the officer, who had probably heard the news, gave him a direct escort into Queens. At the precinct, he and his fellow officers loaded up their vehicles in about 15 minutes, forming a caravan of about six vehicles, and drove along Northern Boulevard into the city. He recalls, “People were actually stepping out from the middle of the street and clapping for us, which was really nice.” The second tower had already collapsed when they entered Manhattan. Near the site, he recalls seeing an injured police officer who was “choking from inhaling all that garbage” (dust & debris). He and his team treated the officer with oxygen and eventually got him into an ambulance. He remembers it took him a long time to connect with his supervisor because of the amount of traffic or “static” on the radio. His supervisor later told them that they lost two teams of about seven people in the collapse of the towers. On 9/11, his main duties were search and rescue around the perimeter of Ground Zero. He states, “I remember finding a foot still in a shoe […] but not much more.” Later, they formed teams to find their vehicles that were not covered with dust, in order to recover larger weapons and more special equipment. He was at Ground Zero till 2 a.m. on 9/12/2001. Glen continued working at Ground Zero from 9/11/2001 to early January 2002. He was put on 16 hour tours, 7 days a week doing recovery work. He remembers taking breaks in temporary headquarters located at Stuyvesant High School off of Chambers and West Street. He remembers one day the E.P.A. did an air quality check in the area and said the air quality was “Ok.” However, Glen states, “I knew the air quality wasn’t good […] I didn’t know it was as toxic as it turned out to be.” He states, “We inhaled and ate contaminated air.” He remembers eating from a buffet with open trays of food and responders forming a line and taking a spoonful of whatever they wanted to eat. He recalls that they had extra socks, underwear and boots, eyewash stations and medical teams to treat small wounds. During his work he states, “We bagged what we thought were body parts, bone fragments, pieces of skin covered with dust […] it got to the point where if you found a bone or piece of flesh you were happy because you knew that they would test it with DNA and the family member of the victim would have a little closure.” Glen particularly felt the loss of his fellow officers after 9/11. He describes, “To me it was like someone coming in and wiping out my family […] I took it really, really hard. "Glen recalls that while working long hours at Ground Zero he did not get to see his kids quite as much. Glen retired from the NYPD in 2003. He missed the camaraderie from the police force, and describes his struggles with PTSD. He mentions this had an impact on his family until he sought help from counseling. He is thankful for the WTC program and the help it offers him.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - Carol L. Paukner oral history interview conducted by Janet Lavelle, April 16, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 004
    Carol, a NYC Transit officer, and her partner were assigned the Broadway and Nassau Street station, located about one block away from the World Trade Center. They were frequently called to respond to the WTC so the call on the morning of September 11th, 2001 wasn’t too unusual until they left the subway a saw the plane sticking out of one of the towers. They quickly confirmed the incident and went to evacuate people from the area. Before the second plane hit, an FBI agent said to Carol “You’re not cowards if you want to leave, there are more planes coming… You’re going to die if you stay here.” Carol responded saying they would not leave; this was her job. Carol proceeded to help and when Tower 2 fell, she was inside holding on for her life. After it fell, she heard the voice of an NYPD traffic officer near her and together they crawled out of the building. It was completely dark and eerily silent. At this point and for years later Carol understand that the towers collapsed around her. In January of 2003, Carol was awarded the Medal of Valor for her efforts on September 11th, 2001. She did not want to accept this medal because she felt defeated. She felt that what she did was not enough but she was forced to go. The ceremony was held at the Winter Garden, right next to the WTC site and when she looked up she remember what had happened to her and finally realized she was caught in the collapse. Carol did not return to do recovery work. She was put on light duty work at her precinct on Canal Street and each day she left work, her car was covered in an inch of dust. She blew out a rotator cuff, had back damage, lung injuries and needed two both knees to be reconstructed. She was forced to retire and she hurts every day. From this interview, Carol hope people remember to live each day to if fullest and to remember why there are so many security measures.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - Jon oral history interview conducted by Melodie Guerrera, April 16, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 005
    Jon, a union ironworker with Local 361, and a group of about 60-80 others arrived at the site on the morning of September 12th with their heavy equipment. They received a police escort through the Battery Tunnel into lower Manhattan. He recalls the first thing many of the ironworkers did after reaching the end of the tunnel was say a prayer. Many of them had never seen a disaster that was an act of war. Despite the police escort, National Guardsmen would not allow them into the job site. But this was a job meant for ironworkers so they pushed their way through, using the heavy machinery to make a trail for other emergency equipment to make their way up West Street. They quickly proved their worth using their heavy equipment to move massive pieces of iron and concrete that the bucket brigade could not move. At the site, Jon recalls the devastation, sirens, jets, and most of all, the blow horns to warn the thousands of responders about the potential for other buildings to fall. He also remembers thinking, someone stuck in the pile won’t last long between the fires and the firemen’s hoses water soaking the area. The first four days, Jon was there as a volunteer with others from his job site in Brooklyn which closed after the attacks. After four days the job reopened, Jon and a few others continued to go down to the pile after their shift until the morning when the returned to work for about a month. He states that he and others were not there to get paid. They were there to try to save lives. Jon blames the government and administration for misleading the public about the hazards at the site and for not having an emergency disaster plan despite the 1993 bombing and the knowledge that an attack would happen again. He is very discouraged by government. He recalls President Bush saying “We will not forget”. But the government has forgotten about the responders’ health. Jon has been disabled since August 4, 2004. He is a strong supporter of unions and without the healthcare provided through the union and the WTC medical monitoring program, he is not so sure he would be alive today. He is no longer working as a result of his 9/11 related illnesses which include PTSD and a 37% reduction in lung capacity. Jon may not be in the best of heath but he would do it again.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Donna Caggiano oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, June 8, 2010, September 13, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 006
    Donna worked as an Electrician for the Local 3 on 9-11-2001. She was one of 50 women in the industry, and is a third-generation electrician. In her 20 years as an electrician she has worked in major construction sites in schools, tunnels, and on bridges. She worked as a fiber splicer and was the first female forewoman at Ground Zero. On 9-11-2001, Donna was at home watching the events on T.V. She knew she would try to go to Ground Zero the next day. She said, “I knew it would be the worst construction site I’d ever seen.” On 9-12-2001, she was working over the 59th St. Bridge and saw there was a bus with volunteer ironworkers heading to Ground Zero. For insurance reasons, electricians had to be “hired” in order to work at Ground Zero, however Donna managed to get on the bus with her apprentice. She remembers carrying her vest and pocket tools on the bus. She recalls that everyone was in a good frame of mind, and that “there was standing room only” on the bus. She saw a lot of chaos at the site. She mentions the lack of equipment, lack of masks—they only had dust masks—but said, “At that moment, it was about saving lives, not equipment.” Donna worked periodically for 24 days at Ground Zero as a Fiber Splicer, and returned again in February 2002 in a hired position. However she mentions her company S&J didn’t like women being down at the site. Donna mentions that she had some PTSD from her experience at Ground Zero. In the future, she advises that people should think about their families before volunteering for experiences like that. (Donna recalls how her own family was upset that she went down to the site). Donna found her job as an electrician very fulfilling and is very proud of the things she has accomplished in life. She is now a grandmother, and was present at this interview with her baby granddaughter.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Marion Holfelder oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, June 8, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 007
    On the morning of September 11th, Marion was at the Brooklyn Criminal Court where she worked as a court officer. The court house was located just across the river from the World Trade Center and in the building, she could smell burning. Not long after she heard about the attacks from a warrant officer’s radio. She was frightened and disoriented. With all the knowledge and security we have in America, how did someone manage to attack? She was directed to evacuate the court house and lock it down. Marion went to the site on September 12th. She was astonished by what she saw. She remembers thinking this is what war looks like; 360 degrees of devastation. There she helped to unload supplies from incoming trucks. She remembers the workers at the site were all numb and it was eerily silent. Everyone pushed aside emotions to get their job done. Adrenaline kept her going. At home, Marion was frightened but at work she felt a sense of relief; it felt cathartic to be a part of the solution. Marion has some health problems and she remembers believing the president when he said we’ll take care of the responders but the responders have been forgotten. She is still concerned that there is another attack whenever she hears sirens. Marion hopes that people remain vigilant and keep their eyes open for more terrorist activity.
    - Moving Images
  - Howard Flynn oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, June 9, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 008